{"tossups": [{"question": "This hero raises a funeral pyre for a man who was drowned by Triton for challenging the gods to a conch shell music contest. He learns that one of his helmsmen never passed onto the underworld because he was not buried. This hero is barely able to recognize the face of a fallen countryman because he is so disfigured, and is rejected by the shade of a dead lover that flees to her deceased husband instead. This hero exits the underworld through an ivory gate of false dreams after being guided by the Cumaean Sibyl. This hero is told by his father Anchises that his descendants will begin a lineage that stretches to Romulus and Julius Caesar. For 10 points, name this title hero of an epic poem by Virgil.", "answer": "Aeneas", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "When the head of this company died, he was buried in a lead-lined coffin in a steel vault, with cement then poured over it to prevent his body from being vandalized. Richard Ely wrote an article claiming Otto von Bismarck's power was \"utterly insignificant\" compared to this company's. Robert Todd Lincoln once served as president of this company, which hired Solon Spencer Beman to design buildings near Lake Calumet, Illinois. An employee cracked that \"we are born in [this company's] house and fed from [this company's] shops\" because of the power it wielded over its company town. A 1894 strike against this company ended when Grover Cleveland sent in the U.S. Army to oppose union leader Eugene V. Debs. For 10 points, name this company whose founder invented a type of railroad sleeping car.", "answer": "Pullman Palace Car Company [or Pullman-Standard Car &amp; Manufacturing Company]", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "In an opera by this composer, a fast, out-of-tune polka played by an onstage piano introduces a scene at a bar, and the opening is structured as a Baroque suite to portray an army captain's inability to understand how the poor live. Another of his operas depicts an arrest, trial, and imprisonment with a silent film. This composer wrote an opera whose protagonist sleeps with Alwa (alva) on the same couch where she had killed his father, Dr. Scho\u0308n (shern), played by the same actor as her own murderer, Jack the Ripper. In another of his operas, the title character drowns himself in the lake next to which he murdered his wife Marie after she was raped by the Drum Major. For 10 points, name this composer of Lulu and Wozzeck (VOT-seck).", "answer": "Alban Berg [or Alban Maria Johannes Berg]", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A poem titled for these things begins, \"From a distant shore they cry, where are all [these things] gone?\" and ends with the command to \"draw your fuel of pain from earth's sated core\". In a Clarice Lispector story, a French explorer in Africa names a seventeen-inch tall pygmy after one of these things. They aren't shadows, but Jeffia Okwe is the protagonist of a novel titled for these things, which are \"for My Land\" in a Wole Soyinka poem. They aren't fruits, but eating these things cause \"mild-eyed melancholy\" men in another poem to declare, \"O rest ye, brother mariners, we will not wander more\". For 10 points, a group of men sing \"our island home is far beyond the wave\" after consuming what things in Tennyson's Homeric poem \"The Lotos-eaters\"?", "answer": "lotus flowers", "subcategory": "Other Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This phenomenon names a molecular beam method developed by I. I. Rabi, who adapted the technique from Otto Stern to measure the magnetic moments and quadrupole moments of many nuclei. The viability of the triple-alpha process was demonstrated by the discovery of a a 7.65 mega\u00c2\u00b7electron\u00c2\u00b7volt phenomenon in carbon to which this term is applied; that was discovered by Fred Hoyle. Recoil-free emission and absorption of gamma rays in the Mo\u0308ssbauer effect is said to be this type of absorption. When the orbital period of two Solar System bodies are related by a ratio of two small integers, they are said to have the orbital type of this term. The Q factor for an RLC circuit is inversely proportional to the frequency named for this term. For 10 points, identify this phenomenon often erroneously claimed to have caused the Tacoma Narrows bridge collapse.", "answer": "resonance [or word forms, such as resonant]", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "A visitor to this place incessantly talks about his stay at Ecclesford with Lord Ravenshaw, which was ruined by the death of a grandmother. That visitor to this place, John Yates, kicks off an event in which residents adopt roles such as Amelia, Agatha, Anhalt, and the Baron. The owner of this place also owns a plantation in Antigua, whose implications of slave labor have been exaggerated by Edward Said. Many of the residents here disobey their father's wishes by acting out the scandalous play Lovers Vows. Henry and Mary Crawford flirt with this estate's residents. It is owned by Sir Thomas Bertram, whose son Edmund eventually marries the shy female protagonist. For 10 points, name this estate where Fanny Price goes to live, the title residence of an 1814 Jane Austen novel.", "answer": "Mansfield Park", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This mathematician names honeycombs and tessellations that use regular and semi-regular shapes to fill a space. Shapes named after Catalan are the duals of the thirteen shapes named after this man, which includes the snub dodecahedron and the rhombicuboctahedron. This man names a property of the real numbers which states that for any real number x, there exists a natural number n greater than x. He tried to calculate how many grains of sand could fill the universe using a \"myriad\" counting system in his book The Sand Reckoner. He also devised a method for calculating the area under a parabola using the method of exhaustion. The formula \"r equals a plus b theta\" in polar coordinates generates his spiral. For 10 points, name this mathematician who also names a principle stating that the weight displaced by a body in a fluid is equal to the buoyant force on it.", "answer": "Archimedes ", "subcategory": "Math", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "Samuel Huntington argued that this event was the starting point of what he considered to be \"the third wave of democratization\". This event led to the permanent closure of the Tarrafal prison camp. The radio broadcast of the songs \"Grandola, Vila Morena\" and \"And after the farewell\" were used to signal the start of this event. After this event, a mass exodus of refugees called retornados occurred due to the decolonization efforts of the National Salvation Junta. The only four deaths during this event were caused by the PIDE secret police, which was disbanded as a result of this event. This event grew out of a coup by the Armed Forces Movement and led to the overthrow of Marcelo Caetano. For 10 points, name this 1974 event that overthrew Portugal's Estado Novo government, named for a type of flower.", "answer": "Carnation Revolution [or Revolution of the Carnations; or Revolucao dos Cravos; or 25th of April Revolution; or Revolucao do 25 de Abril]", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This man constructed a namesake monument after he announced he had no son to keep his name in remembrance, and in later years passersby would throw stones at it. An appeal for this man was made by a woman of Tekoa pretending to be a mourner. He was suckered by Hushai, who gave him intentionally bad advice. After this person died in the Battle of Ephraim's Wood, a ruler shouted \"Would God I had died for thee\" and cried so much that he was chastised by Joab. This man murdered Amnon to avenge the rape of his sister Tamar and he died when his hair was caught in an oak tree, leaving him vulnerable to be killed. This man obtained the treasonous adviser Ahithophel after taking Jerusalem from his father. For 10 points, name this rebellious son of David.", "answer": "Absalom [or Avshalom]", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "This organization's Gaia Project contracts with the NeXtScale System from Lenovo to perform a stereoscopic and kinematic census that maps up to a billion stars in three dimensions. In June 2016, it put two Galileo units into service as part of its long-term plan to operate a competitor to the GPS network. Matt Taylor attracted controversy for a sexual shirt worn during this organization's successful Philae mission. Canada is a \"Cooperating State\" to this group, which routinely uses the Ariane 5. Many of this agency's launches take place from CSG, a site near Kourou in French Guiana, though its science center is in Noordwijk (NORT-vike) and its mission control is in Darmstadt. For 10 points, name this pan- continental agency which sends Germans and Italians into orbit.", "answer": "European Space Agency [or ESA] ", "category": "Current Events"}, {"question": "The work of an economist from this present-day country ignited a controversy during the British election of 1945 because it claimed that England's socialist tendencies mirrored the policies of the Nazi Party. A man who served as the chief economic minister in this country claimed that praxeology, or purposeful deeds, formed the basis of behavior in his book Human Action. A theory of business cycles named after this country argues that booms and busts occur because of the over availability of credit. Ludwig von Mises was an economic minister here, and it was the birthplace of the author of The Road to Serfdom, Friedrich von Hayek. For 10 points, identify this European country that lends its name to a school of individualistic economics.", "answer": "Austria", "category": "Social Science"}, {"question": "A leader during this period refused to take advantage of a salt boycott on his rival's son, claiming to \"not fight with salt, but with the sword\". Another leader from this period put a phrase meaning \"Wind, Forest, Fire Mountain\" on his battle standard and was known as the \"Tiger of Kai\". During this era, Uesugi Kenshin and Takeda Shingen fought each other five times at Kawanaka-jima. This period began with the conflict of the Eastern and Western Armies in the Onin War. The man who brought this era to an end led the Siege of Osaka against the Toyotomis and won the battle of Sekigahara. For 10 points, what time period in Japanese history featured constant conflict between daimyo\u0304s and ended upon the establishment of the Tokugawa shogunate?", "answer": "Sengoku period [or Warring States period; or Sengoku jidai; prompt on Ashikaga shogunate or Muromachi period]", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This place is depicted in the bottom left of four small circles surrounding a larger circle styled as the Eye of God in a \"tabletop\" at the Prado. A doorway leading to this place is lined with toads in another painting. In a depiction of this place, a figure carrying mortar scales a ladder to climb a tower under construction. In another painting, details found in this specific place include a musical fragment inscribed on bare buttocks, a giant knife protruding through ears, and a \"tree-man\" whose torso is formed from a broken eggshell. An enormous cart is hauled to this place in the triptych The Haywain. For 10 points, name this place depicted in the right panels of Bosch's The Last Judgment and The Garden of Earthly Delights, a nightmarish realm.", "answer": "Hell", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The FbaB protein from this genus was split into \"SpyTag\" and \"SpyCatcher\" subunits to produce a molecular superglue. This genus yields a negative pyrrolidonyl (pih-roh-lih-DON-uhl) arylamidase (air-uhl- AM-uh-dace) test and stimulates production of ASLO antibodies. Alexander Bolotin discovered Cas9 in the CRISPR locus of this genus' thermophilus species. The M protein is produced by this genus. Namesake exotoxins secreted by Lancefield Group A members of this genus cause beta-hemolysis. Along with S. aureus, this genus can cause toxic shock syndrome. Bacterial transformation with DNA was demonstrated by Avery, MacLeod (muh-CLOUD), and McCarty in the pneumoniae species of this genus. For 10 points, name this bacterial genus that can cause pharyngitis and scarlet fever with its pyogenes species.", "answer": "Streptococcus [or word forms, such as streptococcal or streptococci] ", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "A character created by this author claims that there is only knowledge and no education after concluding that it is bread, and not religion nor any other ideology, that is the opium of the people. That character of his relays the results of a Notre Dame football game to Sister Cecilia. The ending of a story by this writer contrasts a person who repeats the phrase \"I feel fine\" with her lover, who orders another Anis del Toro and comments on people waiting reasonably for a train. He wrote about a man who tries to convince Jig to have an abortion in Spain. For 10 points, name this American author of \"Hills Like White Elephants\" who also used Spain as the setting for his novel about Robert Jordan, For Whom the Bell Tolls.", "answer": "Ernest Hemingway", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "Gilbert of Mons fudged the story of a death during this war to make the deceased live eight days longer and receive the sacraments. After a man died during this war, his son placed the body in vinegar, but ultimately boiled the flesh from the corpse's bones and buried the bones in Tyre, the heart in Tarsus, and the flesh in Antioch. Because Isaac II Angelos kept blocking the progress of a group in this war, the city of Philippopolis was occupied. During this war, the Battle of Iconium resulted in the fall of the Sultanate of Rum. While trying to cross the Saleph River during this event, Frederick Barbarossa died and thus was unable to meet up with two other monarchs. For 10 points, during what event did King Richard I attempt to recapture Jerusalem?", "answer": "Third Crusade [or Kings Crusade]", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This man's papers were published by Richard Waller, who inelegantly wrote this thinker was \"in person, but despicable\". He accused Henry Oldenburg of spying on him and helping another man steal one of his inventions. Another thinker wrote a letter that compared building on this man's work to \"standing on the shoulders of giants\", possibly a jab at this thinker's short build. There is no authenticated portrait of this man and a persistent myth states that his official portrait was destroyed by the author of Opticks, his rival Isaac Newton. He bitterly fought Christiaan Huygens (HOY-guns) over who really invented a balance-spring watch. This author of Micrographia coined the term \"cell\". For 10 points, what British scientist names a law regarding the force needed to extend a spring?", "answer": "Robert Hooke ", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The fourth movement of the Reformation Symphony begins with this instrument quoting \"A Mighty Fortress Is Our God\". It introduces the main theme of the saltarello in the Italian Symphony, and two of them play the opening notes of the overture to A Midsummer Night's Dream. In a standard orchestra, these instruments sit directly to the right of the oboes. Two of them represent the title river at the start of \"Die Moldau\" from Ma\u0301 vlast, and one of them introduces the opening theme of Bole\u0301ro. This instrument chromatically descends from C-sharp down to G at the start of a tone poem setting of Ste\u0301phane Mallarme\u0301's Prelude to the Afternoon of a Faun. For 10 points, name this instrument whose half- size relative is the piccolo.", "answer": "flute", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "n February 2016, Dialectica controversially published a completely blank article by Tyron Goldschmidt which purportedly demonstrates that absences have this \"power\". This phenomenon, which can be visually represented using \"neuron diagrams\", cannot occur backwards according to the bilking argument. The problems of \"fizzling\" and \"preemption\" arise in probabilistic accounts of this phenomenon. David Lewis introduced the notion of \"comparative similarity\" in a paper which proposed a counterfactual account of this concept. David Hume argued that this concept can only be understood inductively via the \"copy principle\" as it arises from \"constant conjunction\". For 10 points, identify this phenomenon, the necessity of one event resulting in another.", "answer": "causation [or cause and effect; or word forms, such as causality]", "category": "Philosophy"}, {"question": "In a play that begins in this city, a character's complicated proof that a servant is a sheep makes the latter note \"such another proof will make me cry 'baa.'\" In another scene in this city, a character uses a shoe with a hole in it to represent his mother in a long monologue where he berates his dog for not crying. That play features a resident of this city, Julia, swearing a vow of love to the employer of Launce, the idiot servant who owns a dog named Crab. That play begins in this city but features the young men Valentine and Proteus leaving it to expand their horizons. In another play set here, Prince Escalus tries to stop the Montagues and Capulets from feuding. For 10 points, what Italian city is the setting of Shakespeare's Romeo and Juliet, as well as a comedy about \"two gentlemen\" from here?", "answer": "Verona", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "Kit Fine holds that this field can be explained by non-causal dependencies known as \"grounds\". \"Revisionary\" and \"descriptive\" approaches to this field are contrasted in P. F. Strawson's book Individuals. This field titles a book which posits that a statue is different from a lump of bronze by virtue of its cause, illustrating its author's theory of hylomorphism. The thesis that this field \"affords us knowledge of a transcendent reality\" is rejected as unverifiable in the first chapter of Language, Truth, and Logic. The logical positivists sought to \"eliminate\" this field which was called \"first philosophy\" in a namesake book describing the \"unmoved mover\" written by Aristotle. For 10 points, name this branch of philosophy concerned with the fundamental nature of the world.", "answer": "metaphysics", "subcategory": "Philosophy Other", "category": "Philosophy"}], "bonuses": []}